115 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST FOR UNIVERSITY ADMISSIONS
（大学入学共通考试 115天前）
Mamemameshi from ancient literature.
黑板上这句古文“勤勤恳恳”
What do you think it means?
你们觉得是什么意思？
-You. -Huh?
-你 -什么？
Mamemameshi, right? Uh, um…
“勤勤恳恳”就是…呃…
Totally clueless as usual.
和平常一样 真是什么都不知道呢
-Alright, you. -Serious or sincere.
-那么 你 -认真或是真挚
That's right. Listen, everyone.
没错 听着 大家
Write ancient literature in kanji!
用汉字来写古文！
Huh?
什么？
Is that how you write mamemameshi?
这就是它的写法吗？
It is easier to understand in kanji.
汉字易懂多了
Yes. Ancient words are hard to understand in hiragana.
没错 古文用平假名来写比较难懂
But if you write them in kanji, they're remarkably easy.
但如果用汉字写出来就会简单易懂
They're not lost in the past.
它们不是留在过去的文字
They're still used today. Think of it that way and it's easier.
而是现在还可以使用 这么想就会容易多了
Toshi means "fast."
这个词的意思是“快”
Shirushi means "to be clear."
这个的意思是“显著”
Yoshinashi means "no reason."
这则是“无理由”
Wow, that does make sense.
哇 这就说得通了
Ancient literature is still Japanese.
古文仍然是日文
Do not fear it.
别害怕它
The difference between understanding and not understanding math
理解与不理解数学的区别
is whether you can prove it or not.
是看你能不能证明它
In the UTokyo entrance exam, you may be asked to prove the formula.
东大入学试中 可能会要求你证明一项公式
But your math is like a bucket full of holes.
但你们的数学能力 就像个漏洞百出的水桶
What? You mean useless?
什么？你的意思是没用？
What happens if you put water in a bucket full of holes?
你将水倒进一个 满是洞口的水桶 会发生什么？
-It all leaks out, of course. -Yeah!
-它当然会漏出来了 -对啊
Math is a cumulative subject.
数学是门积累的科目
Basic arithmetic. Pythagorean theorem. Quadratic function.
四则运算、勾股定理、二次函数
Learn to prove junior high level formulas.
学习怎么去证明初中水平的公式
Then you'll be able to prove high school level formulas.
你就会能证明高中水平的公式
You've no time to sit and stare.
你们没时间在这发呆了
-Get it together! -Yes, sir!
-快给我开始！ -是！
-Rote memorization? -Yes!
-硬背？ -对！
For example,
比如说
Memorize phrases like this.
记得这样的短句
You know what it means, right? Amano.
你明白这句话的意思吧？天野
"This will expand my perspective."
“这将拓展我的视野”
This can be used in any free English essay.
这句话可用于任何的自由英语作文中
-It's a magic phrase. -Magic?
-是个魔法短句 -魔法？
For example, if you're asked, "What do you think of studying abroad?"
比如说 要是它问你 “你觉得出国留学怎么样？”
You can say, "Going overseas will develop my point of view," right?
你可以说“出国留学 将拓展我的视野” 对吧？
If you're asked about the pros and cons of pets.
要是它问你养宠物的好处和坏处
"Interacting with animals
“与动物互动
will develop my point of view." You can use this.
将拓展我的视野” 你在这里也可以用它
-Ah, I see. -Here's more.
-这样啊 我明白了 -还有更多
"If this situation continues…"
“要是这个情况继续…”
"This makes it possible for A to do something."
“这使得A能够做某些事情”
Yes, memorize these phrases in full.
是 把这些短句整句背下来
-Yes, ma'am. -Entrance exams don't need individuality.
-是 -入学考试不要求个性
If there is a formula, you should use it.
要是有公式 就该利用公式
If you use the reading comprehension skills you've built, it'll be simple.
运用之前建立的阅读理解能力 这就很简单了
Use "This enables A to…"
用“This enables A to…”
and write a sentence meaning, "Time will solve their problems."
写一个句子 表达“时间会解决他们的问题”
Write a sentence like that.
写一句这样的句子
There are 115 days until the Common Test.
距离共通考试还有115天
How's the Special Course?
东大专科怎么样了？
Everything is going fine. Don't worry.
一切都进行得很顺利 不用担心
Everyone has acquired basic academic skills.
大家都掌握了基本的知识
It will get even better from here.
接下来会渐入佳境的
Yeah? That's good.
是吗？那我就安心了
I know it means I'm out of a job.
这也代表我会失业了
Why did I enter such a contract?
我为什么要签这样的合同呢？
Chairman…
理事长…
I feel sorry for your office too.
对你的事务所 我也很抱歉
If everyone gets into UTokyo, the school will be gone.
要是大家都考上东大 学校就会关闭
The Mizuno Law Office contract will fall through.
水野事务所的合同也会告吹
My practice was just starting to get going.
事务所才刚刚开始
But I've thought about it.
不过我想过了
A high school is a place where, when the students grow up,
高中是学生长大后
they can come back to that place.
能够回去的地方
For me, it's Ryuzan High School.
对我来说 那是龙山高中
When I'm facing challenges,
当我遇到挑战时
my memories of my hard work there support me.
我曾在那努力的回忆总是支持着我
If that place ceased to exist…
如果那个地方不复存在…
Yes, I'm sure not having a place to go back to is sad.
对啊 没有能够回去的地方 是一件悲伤的事情
I feel bad for the students who joined because of my philosophy on education.
我为那些因为我的教育理念 而入学的学生感到难过
All those first and second-year students.
那些一年级和二年级的学生
I don't want to put them in this position because of adult issues.
我不想因为大人的问题 把他们置于这种境地
Can't we do something?
就没有我们能做的事吗？
Now that you mention it.
既然你提到了
Actually, I noticed something.
其实 我注意到了一些事
-What? -May I?
-什么？ -我能说吗？
If five or more students get into UTokyo, you've got to step down.
要是五位以上的学生考进东大 理事长就得离职
And Mr. Takahara will join the board. That's the contract?
高原老师就会加入理事会 这是之前说好的 对吧？
Yes, that's it.
对 是这样
I think the selection of the chairman will come up at the next meeting.
我想下次的会议会决定理事长的人选
There, Principal Okuda or Mr. Takahara could volunteer for the position.
那时奥田校长和高原老师可以自荐
-Me? -Um…
-我？ -这个…
In order to sell the school, the chairman must approve.
出售学校必须经过理事长的同意
So if one of you becomes chairman,
所以要是你们其中一位成了理事长
we can protect the land and the school.
我们就能保住这片土地还有学校了
I see.
原来如此
According to the school's articles of endowment,
根据学校的捐赠条款
the chairman is selected by the board's majority vote.
理事长由理事会的多数票选出
There are five board members.
一共有五位理事
So if Mr. Okuda and Mr. Takahara oppose, we just need one more vote.
要是奥田校长和高原老师反对 我们只需要再争取多一票
And one of them can become the chairman.
他们其中一位就能当上理事长
A pro-sale person can't become the chairman.
支持出售的人不能当上理事长
Someone other than myself and the principal.
除了我和校长以外的人
Who can we pull over to our side?
我们要再拉拢一个人过来？
I see. The former chairman and his external advisor
这样啊 前任理事长和他的外部理事
are in favor of selling. We must target the former principal.
支持出售 我们得瞄准前校长
Then it's okay.
那就没问题了
Unlike Okuda, he never betrayed me.
和奥田不同 他从来没背叛过我
Is it that simple?
有这么简单吗？
We need to very carefully involve the former principal.
要涉及前校长 我们需要格外小心
Leave that to me.
交给我吧
I will convince the former principal.
我会说服前校长
-You're so dependable! -Yes, sir.
-你真是可靠！ -是
-Principal, I'm counting on you. -Yes!
-校长 我就靠你了 -是！
I'm sorry!
对不起！
Who was here yesterday talking big?
昨天是谁在这里信誓旦旦？
I was too late.
我去的太迟了
Mr. Komatsugawa was already on the former chairman's side.
小松先生已经站在前任理事长那边了
He must've paid him off. He's so dirty.
他一定是给了他钱 真是下流
Of the five members, three will side with the former chairman.
五位理事中会有三位支持前理事长
They are sure to choose someone in favor of the sale for chairman.
他们肯定会选一位 支持出售的人当理事长
You seem disappointed for another reason.
你的失望看来另有原因
Huh? No.. but I'm sure there must be another way.
什么？不…但肯定还有其它方法的
I'll see if I can find another solution.
我再看看能不能找其它解决方法
Don't get it twisted. Your job is to get those kids into UTokyo.
别搞错重点了 你的工作是把那些孩子们送上东大
Of course it is.
当然
But if they work hard and pass,
但要是他们努力学习并且考上了
their alma mater will close. That's so sad.
结果母校却没有了 这太悲伤了
My memories of Ryuzan will stay with me forever.
我在龙山的回忆一直伴随着我
That time I tore up my answer sheet
那次我撕掉了答卷
and you retrieved it. That's why I'm here now.
你把它补了回来 这就是我现在站在这里的原因
It's not a simple thing to abandon your school.
抛弃学校不是一件简单的事
It's unacceptable for it to disappear just so adults can make money.
成年人为了赚钱 而让它消失 我没法接受
Our trainees Kohashi and Iwai will be here next year, working hard.
还有练习生小桥和岩井 明年也会参与 一起努力
We can't interfere with their learning.
我们不能影响他们学习
I want to try my very best.
我想尽力去尝试
I'll stake my life.
我会拿我的人生做赌注
Ms. Tamura, where are the documents relating to the articles of endowment?
田村老师 捐赠条款的有关文件放在哪？
-Articles of endowment? -Can I see them?
-捐赠条款？ -我能看看吗？
Over here.
在这里
Everything in these shelves.
都在这柜子里
Thank you very much.
谢谢
Huh? What's this?
咦？这是什么？
The Common Test for University Admissions. In other words,
大学入学共通考试 也就是说
the first UTokyo entrance exam form.
第一次东大入学试的申请书
-Oh. -This is it.
-哦 -就是这个啊
-I can feel my back straighten. -My hands are shaking.
-我感觉自己背都挺直了 -我手在抖
Everyone has theirs?
大家都拿到了吗？
Okay, check that the university and department names are correct.
好 检查志愿校名 和应考类组是否正确吧
A year ago, could any of you have imagined this day?
你们有谁在去年的现在 曾想像过今天的景象？
I know for a fact that you've all exceeded your own expectations.
我知道的是 你们都超出了自己的预期
That's who you are now.
你们现在就是那样的人
This application form will decide your future.
这次申请会改变你们的未来
It will be your passport.
它会成为你们的通行证
Write with all your heart, with sincerity and care.
全心全意地 小心地去写
-Especially Seto. -I know!
-特别是濑户 -我知道啦！
Carefully, right?
小心地写 对吧？
After you've filled it out, check for mistakes.
填写好后 查看有没有错误
Check it three times.
检查三次
Three times?
三次？
Kenta. I'll check with you.
健太 我和你一起检查
Okay.
好
Next, have your parents…
接下来 请你们的父母…
Oh, Seto, you can ask your sister.
濑户 你可以请你姊姊
-Okay. -Have someone else check it.
-好 -一定要给第三方确认
Then make a copy and keep it with you.
然后复印一份 自己收着
-Got it? -Yes, sir.
-明白了吗？ -是
Fujii, got it?
藤井 了解了吗？
Of course I do.
了解
Ms. Mizuno, I'm going home.
水野老师 我回家了
Good night.
辛苦了
Sho and Kyo were awarded for a thesis again?
祥和峡的论文又获奖了？
-Yes, they were. -I'm so proud of my sons.
-是 他们又获奖了 -不愧是我的儿子们
Compared to them, Ryo is…
和他们比起来 辽…
It seems he's trying for UTokyo,
看来他想考东大
I know he'll never make it.
反正他不可能考上的
We had such high hopes for high school,
我们那时对他的高中入学考 抱那么大希望
and he caught a cold.
他竟然感冒了
He cracks under pressure. It's pathetic.
正式上场就考差 真是可悲
Listen, everyone. Until test day,
听着了 大家 直到考试那天
ignore all extra opinions and information.
别去听那些多余的意见和信息
Shut out the noise of the world.
和世界的噪音隔绝
In two weeks, there's a practice exam.
两周后会有一场模拟考试
The last one.
正式考试前最后一次了
You'll take it as if it's the real thing.
你们要用正式上场的心态去考
-The last one. -I'm getting nervous.
-最后一次 -我开始紧张了
How do we act like it's the real thing?
要怎样表现 才能像考正式的考试一样？
Right. I'm going to tell you.
对 我现在就跟你们说
Five Rules to Prep for the Common Test.
共通考试的心态五大守则
Yeah! Here we go.
好！来了！
Finally, the Five Rules!
久等了 五大守则！
Number one.
第一
Until the end of the second day, don't think about subjects you've finished.
直到第二天结束之前 都别去想考过的科目
But I'll wonder if I've gotten the questions right.
但我会想自己有没有答对那些问题
What will you do if you realize a mistake during a different test?
要是想起了 另一场考试的错误 你会怎样？
I think I might freak out.
我想我会很慌乱吧
Right? You're not the only one.
对吧？不只是你
Listen. If even a single mistake
听着 就连一个错误
starts to bother you, it will make you feel uneasy.
也会影响你 让你感到不安
If it's your last chance, the effect is worse.
一想到正式考试没有退路 结果会更糟
I see.
原来如此
During breaks,
考试休息期间
listen to music with earphones.
用耳机听音乐
Shut out the voices around you.
将自己和周边的声音隔离起来
After the first day is over, all the subjects of that day
第一天结束后 那天考的科目
should be wiped from your mind.
应该要从你脑袋里消失
Wipe them from my mind.
从我脑袋里消失
Number two. Don't get bogged down by difficult questions.
第二 不要被难题困住
The Common Test always has one really difficult question.
共通考试总会有一道非常困难的题目
-Is that true? -But don't worry.
-真的吗？ -但不用担心
A question that's difficult for you is going to be difficult for everyone.
这题目对你来说困难 对其他所有人也一样
The average mark for that subject will be lower.
那科目的平均分就会被拉低
The faster you can change gears, the better your chances.
速度调整得越快 你的机会就越大
But if you can solve it, you could get ahead of others.
但要是能解那道题 就会超越其他人
That is true. But the Common Test has a lot of questions.
你说得对 但共通考试有很多道题
If you spend time thinking, you might find the answer
如果花时间思考 你可能会找到答案
but you don't have time for that.
但没有那种时间
Prioritize questions where you are sure to get the points.
优先处理能确实得分的题目
Do what you know first.
先做我会的题
Number three. Go home alone after day one.
第三 第一天结束后独自回家
You mean we can't meet anyone?
你是说 我们不能见其他人？
Aw, that's lonely!
什么啊 那会很孤单耶！
You guys really are close.
你们俩真是要好
Listen.
听好了
Just seeing a friend, even if they don't ask how it went,
单单是见到朋友 即使他们没问考得怎么样
you'll be able to tell how the other did.
你也能看出他们表现得怎么样
Little things like that will make you feel uneasy.
那种小事也会让你感到不安
-Nao is like an open book after all. -Hey.
-毕竟菜绪都把情绪写在脸上了 -喂
Don't contact each other.
别互相联络
No messaging, no phone calls.
不发短信 不打电话 全都禁止
-Yes, sir. -And number four.
-是 -第四
Always write the answer on your question sheet.
务必将答案写在试卷上
It's a multiple-choice test, so just circle the numbers.
因为是划卡作答 把答案圈起来就好了
After the day is done, you can check your answers.
这是为了考完当天立马对答案
We've already been doing that for the practice exams.
这跟之前的模拟考一样 没问题
Right? But for the real thing, you have the secondary exam.
对吧？不过真正的考验在第二次考试
The UTokyo entrance exam application form depends on this.
这会影响到如何填写 东大正式入学试申请书
What do you mean?
什么意思？
Based on your Common Test results,
你会根据共通考试的成绩
you submit your UTokyo secondary exam application.
来提交东大二试的考试申请
Based on your score, to avoid the cutoff,
根据你的分数 为了避免被刷下来
you might need to change your stream.
你可能需要转组
But the Common Test results arrive
但共通考试的成绩
after the secondary exam application is due.
在二试申请截止后才会公布
So you'll use your self-graded score
所以你们要使用自己评分的分数
and look at the cutoff points to decide how to submit your application.
观察申请门槛的状况 来决定怎么填写申请书
That's why you mark down your answers.
要你们把答案记下来的原因就是这个
How do you know the cutoff point?
怎么知道申请门槛是多少？
You can check the UTokyo website.
那可以在东大的官网上查到
Website?
官网？
Every year, UTokyo uploads the number of applicants to their website.
东大每年都会在官网上公布申请人数
And it gets updated every day.
而且每天都会更新数字
Examinees wait until the last minute to submit,
考生们会等到最后一刻才提交申请
looking at the numbers and deciding what the cutoff might be.
观察那些数字 推断出申请门槛
Consider ratio versus capacity
考量招募人数的倍率
and you can determine where the cutoff point will be.
判断该类组会不会进行第一轮筛选
Examinees can look at which stream has more and submit their forms.
可以看看哪个类组有较多考生申请 再根据提交入学考申请
Wow, I didn't know that.
哇 我都不知道
You can find out how many rivals you have?
我们能知道自己有多少对手？
On the other hand,
另一方面
you can shoot for the place with the fewest rivals.
也能瞄准那些没什么竞争对手的地方
And number five.
第五
I've saved the most important for last.
我把最重要的留到最后
Entrance exams are about facing yourself.
入学试就是要面对自己
Others don't matter.
其他人无关紧要
Go into it with only your own success in mind.
用自己能考上就行的心态应考
-That's all. -Yes, sir.
-以上 -是
FINAL PRACTICE EXAM
（最后一次的模拟考试）
Now, please begin.
现在 请开始
Have you found what you needed?
你找到需要的信息了吗？
No, it's tough going.
还没有 进行得很不顺利
Do you need some help?
你需要帮助吗？
This is my job as a lawyer, so…
这是我作为律师的工作 所以…
Is that you, Fujii?
这不是藤井吗？
Whoa, that bag.
哇 那书包
You're at Tatsumi Gakuen? Isn't it full of idiots?
你念龙海学园？ 那里不是都是笨蛋吗？
A Tatsumi student trying to get into UTokyo?
难道龙海生想上东大？
Your brothers are super smart, aren't they?
你的哥哥们超级聪明的 是吧？
Poor thing!
好可怜喔
If I study with those idiots, I might catch it. The stupidity.
和这些笨蛋一起学习 我可能会染上他们的愚蠢
I can't stand dumb girls. I'll catch the dumb.
我受不了笨女生 会被传染变笨的
This worm could never aim for UTokyo.
这只虫子是不可能想上东大的
No comeback? How boring.
不反击吗？真无聊
Oh no, it's almost time.
啊 差不多了
The kids should be coming back soon.
孩子们快要回来了
We'll do that. You go on.
我们来做吧 你继续
Sorry. Thank you very much.
不好意思 谢谢你们
What are you doing here?
你在这干嘛？
We all promised to go back together and you went alone.
大家约好一起回去 但你一个人走了
-You followed me? -Yeah.
-你跟着我吗？ -嗯
I don't need that.
我不需要
Fujii. Your face is different. You look stressed.
藤井的表情跟平常不一样 很紧张
Huh?
什么？
You're always pleasant. I'm jealous.
你总是那么自在 我真羡慕
I wish I could be like you.
我希望自己能像你一样
Huh? Me?
什么？我？
Yeah. You say what you're thinking.
嗯 你总是把你的想法说出来
I don't know what to say.
我不知道该说什么
People at UTokyo share their opinions.
东大里的人会分享自己的意见
Fujii, it'll suit you.
藤井 那很适合你
I think so too.
我也是这么想的
Yeah.
嗯
Thanks.
谢谢
Let's go back to class.
回去教室吧？
Yeah.
也是
Ugh. I thought I did better than that.
啊 我以为我会考更高
Me too. My score has barely changed.
我也是 我分数几乎没变
I thought I worked pretty hard.
我以为我已经很努力了
Damn. I thought that was my best one yet.
可恶 这是我最有把握的一次耶
What do you think is the time when people feel the worst?
你们觉得人在什么时候会最不甘心？
Huh? Must be times like this?
什么？一定是这种时候吧
Yes. When you're working hard and you don't get results.
没错 当你很努力却没成果的时候
Especially studying for entrance exams, it takes time to see results.
特别是入学试的学习 需要时间来才能看到成果
So don't feel down.
所以别沮丧了
Sir, do you think we feel down?
老师 你觉得我们沮丧吗？
-Huh? -We don't have time to feel down.
-什么？ -我们没时间沮丧
I'm going to crush my mistakes.
我要粉碎我的错误
I found out what I don't know so I feel lucky!
不如说找到了自己不明白的东西 所以我觉得很幸运！
If you get that, you'll be okay.
要是你们明白这点 就没问题了
Listen.
听好了
You might feel bad now, but working towards your UTokyo goal is happiness.
也许现在会觉得很痛苦 但可以向东大努力可是很幸福的
-Yeah. -Having a goal is happiness…
-对啊 -有目标是幸福的…
Happy!
幸福！
Just keep believing your breakthrough will come.
继续相信 你们就能突破
It's tough now, but keep fighting.
现在很艰难 但继续加油
Yes, sir!
是！
Kohashi and Iwai, you too.
小桥和岩井 你们也一样
We still have a month, right? We won't give up.
我们还有一个月 对吧？ 我们不会放弃的
Of course not! If we fail, we'll do it next year.
当然不会了！ 要是失败了 我们明年再来一次
That's the spirit.
这精神就对了
I guess there's nothing.
找不到啊
C'mon…
拜托了…
Hm?
咦？
IMPORTANT DOCUMENTS WITHIN
（内有重要资料）
ARTICLES OF ENDOWMENT ADDITIONAL APPLICATION
（捐赠条款 追加申请资料）
Wow.
太好了
Wow, wow, wow, wow.
太好了…
You're late! Why did you suddenly call us here?
你太慢了！干嘛突然叫我们过来？
I don't just call myself a lawyer for show.
我可不是虚有其名的律师
I, Naomi Mizuno,
我 水野直美
have found the clue to preventing the school sale!
找到了阻止学校出售的线索
Huh? Really?
咦？真的吗？
-What do you mean? Explain yourself! -It's this, here!
-这是什么意思？快解释 -是这个
ARTICLES OF ENDOWMENT ALTERATION APPROVAL
（学校法人捐赠条款变更认可书）
I didn't know there was such a rule.
我不知道还有这一项条款
Oh! It's a miracle!
哦！是奇迹啊！
-We can use this, Mizuno! -Yeah!
-我们能用上这个 水野！ -对啊
Leave it to me to explain it to the faculty members.
交给我吧 我会和教职员们解释
Yes, please do. I'm sure they're against it.
是 拜托你了 我想大家都会反对的
Yes, ma'am.
是
35 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 35天前）
30 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 30天前）
If I hadn't joined the UTokyo Special Course,
如果没有加入东大专科
what would I be doing now?
不知道我会变成什么样子
30 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 30天前）
25 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 25天前）
I wasn't that serious about it when I joined,
加入的时候 其实我并不是很认真
but I'm glad I took the first step.
但我很庆幸自己迈出了第一步
25 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 25天前）
20 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 20天前）
Thinking about when I got tossed in the sea,
想到了那时我被丢进海里
I've changed since then.
从那以后我就改变了
20 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 20天前）
15 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 15天前）
"To say."
“说”
I thought the Olympics were my only dream.
我一直以为奥运会是我唯一的梦想
But that's not my whole life.
但我的人生不只如此
15 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 15天前）
10 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 十天前）
Ever since I decided to go to UTokyo together with everyone,
自从我决定和大家一起去东大后
every day is so much fun.
每天都过得很有意思
I want to go to UTokyo with everyone. I'm going to do it!
我想和大家一起上东大 我绝对要考上！
10 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 十天前）
Alright, next question. What's the symbol for nitrogen?
下一题 氮的化学符号是？
I just did that. Um… wait…
我刚刚才读过 呃…等等…
Happy Henry Lives Beside Boron Cottage… Hm? Uh…
但你生屁屁…嗯？呃…
-Time out! -Augh!
-时间到！ -啊！
5 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 五天前）
3 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 三天前）
It's the Common Test. I've got to pass it with ease.
是共通考试 我一定要轻松通过
GET INTO UTOKTO!! SCIENCES 2
（目标考进东大！理科二类）
I will…
我…
…definitely pass!
一定要考上！
JANUARY 2022 3 DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（2022年1月 大学入学共通考试 三天前）
THE DAY BEFORE THE COMMON TEST
大学入学共通考试 一天前）
DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 一天前）
Finally, tomorrow is the real Common Test.
终于 明天就是真正的共通考试了
Now, I want each of you to tell me what you want to do at UTokyo.
现在 我想你们每一位告诉我 你们想在东大做什么
Huh? That's a bit sudden.
什么？也太突然了
Put it into words and clarify your goals.
组织语言 把你们的目标明确表达出来
By sharing it with others,
通过和其他人分享
you create some good pressure.
你们会产生一些正向的动力
-Let's start with you, Seto. -Me?
-从你开始吧 濑户 -我？
I'm gonna go to UTokyo,
我会去东大
and figure out how to make money selling ramen.
研究出卖拉面赚钱的方法
I want to help my sister.
我想帮我姊姊减轻负担
I want to enjoy being a UTokyo student.
我想要享受作为东大生的乐趣
You said it, didn't you?
老师你说过的 对吧？
"Find what you want to do at UTokyo."
“找出你想在东大做的事情”
I want to meet lots of people
我想遇见很多人
and find what I want to do.
再找出我想做的事情
I've decided. I'm going to get into UTokyo and the Olympics too.
我决定了 我会考上东大和参加奥运会
I'm going to make it happen.
我绝对会达成的
I want
我要
to prove that even a guy like me can get into UTokyo.
证明即使是我这样的人也能考上东大
And then I think I'll be able to be confident.
多少建立一些自信心
That's where I'll start.
所以要从这里开始
I want to be a researcher.
我想当一名研究员
To make a world where insects and people live together.
创造一个人和昆虫共存的世界
I'm going to keep studying.
我会继续学习
I love reading books.
我真的很爱读书
I want to read all the valuable literature at UTokyo.
我想在阅读东大全部有价值的文学
And then I'll find a job where I can use that.
然后 我会找一份可以运用它的工作
I… want to help someone.
我…我想帮助某个人
I want to be needed by someone.
我想被人需要
I'm going to take over the family business.
我会继承家业
But I like studying now.
但我现在很喜欢学习
I want to study more!
我想学得更多！
I…
我…
What, you can't say it?
怎么？你说不出口？
You want to show your parents and brothers.
你想证明给你父母和哥哥们看
Is that why?
这不就是你考东大的理由吗？
Yeah.
没错
I'll get into UTokyo no matter what.
我无论如何都会上东大
I'll be so important that you guys will be speechless!
我会变成重要人物 重要得你们哑口无言
What?
干嘛？
Listen. By going to UTokyo,
听好了 考上了东大
your futures will be full of endless possibilities.
你们的未来会充满无穷的可能性
Others don't decide your future.
你们的未来不由其他人来决定
You don't have to follow the status quo.
你们不需要遵循社会的现状
You make your life yourself.
你们能创造属于自己的人生
It's not what happens to you in life, it's what you do!
重要的不是人生中发生了什么 而是你们做了什么！
Big and strong, take that step!
大步而坚定 迈出你们的脚步吧！
Take that step with all your might!
尽你们的全力迈出这一步！
It's finally time for battle.
终于到了战斗时刻
Seize victory.
抓住胜利吧
So it starts tomorrow.
明天终于要开始了
It takes me back.
好像回到了从前
Back then, my mom collapsed.
那时 我妈倒下了
I felt like giving up so many times.
有很多次我都想放弃
But Yajima and everyone supported me.
但矢岛和大家支持了我
These kids too,
这些孩子也一样
I hope they will support each other.
我希望他们能互相支持
Comrades with the same goals.
拥有相同目标的战友
I'm sure their feelings are connected.
一定能互相理解
Yes.
是啊
I always think this, but at times like this,
我常常这么想 但这种时候
all we can do is pray.
我们能做的就只有祈祷了
-That's fine, isn't it? -Huh?
-这样也很好 不是吗？ -什么？
I'm sure they'll be just fine.
他们一定可以的
Believe in your students.
相信你的学生吧
Yes, sir!
是
Sir.
老师
Do you remember what you told me when I thought I'd give up?
你还记得在我快放弃考试时 你对我说了什么吗？
Hm?
什么？
You told me "Do your best."
你跟我说：“尽力加油”
Those words support me even now.
这些话直到现在都支撑着我
Thank you very much.
真的很谢谢
And thanks for now on as well.
接下来也请你多指教了
DAY 1 OF THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 第一天）
This is it, the final battle.
就是现在了 最后的战斗
-Yeah! -Uh-huh.
-嗯 -哦
Let's do our best.
今天要全力以赴
Okay!
好！
-Here we go! -Yeah!
-我们上吧！ -好！
DRAGON ZAKURA UTOKYO ACCEPTANCE PRAYER
（龙樱 祈愿通过东大入学试）
It's time for them to start.
开始考试了吧
Yes. I'm getting nervous.
是啊 我也开始紧张了
Do you think five or more will pass?
你认为会有五位以上通过吗？
If they don't, there'll be trouble.
要是他们没通过可就麻烦了
We've solved our problem.
我们解决了这边的问题
Now we have to work at rebuilding the school.
接下来得着手重建学校
It's finally the day!
这天终于到了！
Whoa, everyone is so uptight.
啊 大家都好紧绷
But I took six practice exams.
但我已经考过了六次模拟考
I'm used to this feeling.
我已经习惯这种感觉了
It's just like a badminton game.
就像羽球比赛
This nervousness helps me focus.
这种紧张感反倒能让我专注
The first day is English, lit, and history.
第一天是英语、语文和历史
It's okay. Those are my best subjects.
没事的 这些都是我擅长的科目
Calm down. Just do the work.
冷静 只管做吧
After all, I've got good luck!
反正我运气很好！
Just do as I always do.
像平时一样做就好了
I'm with everyone. It's okay.
我和大家在一起 没问题的
I can do it. I can do it.
我能做到…
I can absolutely do it!
我绝对能做到！
DAYS UNTIL THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 还有零天）
Maybe I should've gone to cheer them on?
早知道应该去给他们打气的
You'd just be in the way. They can fight alone.
你去了只是碍事 他们已经能独立迎战了
We've already done what we can.
我们能做的都做了
Yes, I know.
是 我知道
The only thing we can do now is trust the students, right?
我们现在能做的 就只有相信学生 对吧？
It's alright. They'll get the points to pass.
没问题 他们会考到及格分的
Alright, please begin.
好 请开始
Oh! I just reviewed this last week.
哦！我上周才复习过这个
I sure am lucky.
我的确很幸运呢
Ptolemy's world map is a conic projection, so it's number three or four.
托勒密世界地图是圆锥投影图 所以答案是三或四
Start the lit exam with the classics.
语文考试从古文题做起
After "in other words"
“换句话说”之后
comes a paraphrasing sentence.
是改述句
LUNCH BREAK
（午休）
Snacks, snacks!
零食！
"Don't think about subjects you've finished" is what he said.
老师说过：“别去想考过的科目”
How was the Jokyu War question?
承久之乱那一题是什么？
I said Emperor Go-Toba was exiled to Sado.
我写后鸟羽天皇被流放到佐渡
-Right? Ah, it's wrong. -What?
-对吧？啊 错了 -什么？
He was exiled to Oki.
他被流放到隐岐才对
Oh no! I put Sado!
哎呀！我选了佐渡！
I couldn't get the Kansei Reforms question either.
宽政改革那题我也不太会
The answer… Ah, forget it!
那题的答案是…啊 别想了！
He told us "Don't think about subjects you've finished!"
他让我们“别去回想考过的科目！”
Don't take notes during listening.
听力考试时不要记笔记
What did this word mean?
这个词是什么意思？
No, if I think it's difficult, it'll be difficult for everyone else too.
不 要是我觉得难 对其他人来说也是一样的
If I have time later, I'll work on it.
如果待会有时间 我再花时间想
Don't think about other things. Focus on the exam!
别想其它事 专注考试！
After day one, go home alone.
第一天考试之后独自回家
Don't contact each other.
别联络其他人
I wish I could see everyone,
真希望能见见大家
but I know that everyone's working hard, so I'm not lonely.
但我知道大家都在努力 我并不孤单
I did alright in English…
我英语做得不错…
It's important for me to face myself now.
现在面对自己很重要
Mari!
麻里！
No… Go home alone.
不行…要自己回家
The English questions were hard.
英语的题目很困难
The ancient literature tripped me up…
古文的部分难倒我了…
But I did what I could…
但我已经尽力了…
Hey, are you telling us to play basketball?
喂 你叫我们来打篮球啊？
I am. We going to have a free-throw shoot-off.
对 我们来玩自由投篮
Who will go against me? The rules are simple.
谁来当我的对手？规则很简单
Ten shots, the higher score wins.
十次投篮 高分者胜
Sounds fun. I'll do it.
听起来很有趣 我玩
Rock, paper, scissors.
石头、剪刀、布
Alright.
来了
-Miss! Miss! -What? You're terrible.
-失败！ -什么啊？你好差
You're the one who wanted to play.
老师 是你自己说要玩的
-You look bad! -This is fine.
-真是难下台！ -这没什么
-Alright! -Go Akira!
-来了！ -辉 加油！
-Hey! -Oh!
-嘿！ -哦！
-Wow, Seto! -Yay!
-真厉害 濑户！ -耶！
-Nice! -Hey! Hey!
-棒！ -嘿！
-Sir, do your best! -Sir, get a point!
-老师 加油 -老师 要得分哦
Are you even trying?
你到底有没有认真啊？
-Alright! -Oh! Good one.
-好耶！ -哦！好球！
-Wow, wow! -Nice shot!
-哇！ -投得好！
-Great! -You got three in a row!
-厉害！ -你一连进了三球！
Wow!
厉害啊！
Akira, don't lose now!
辉 现在别输了！
You can still win!
你还能赢的！
So close!
差一点！
-Akira, last one. -Uh-huh.
-辉 最后一球 -嗯
-Get that last one! -Do it!
-最后一球要投进去哦 -加油
Mr. Sakuragi, six points. Seto, five points.
樱木老师六分 濑户五分
-Mr. Sakuragi wins! -Damn it!
-樱木老师赢了 -可恶
That was a close one, Seto.
差一点而已 濑户
You could've won if you kept it up.
如果保持前半场的气势 你就赢了
Nah, it was just bad luck.
那是运气不好而已
It's not just luck.
那不只是运气
You messed up when it mattered
关键时刻 你搞砸了
because you tried to score every time.
因为你每次都想得分
Huh? It's a contest though.
咦？但这是场比赛啊
You're supposed to try to score every time.
本来就该争取每次都得分
The reason I won is because I only tried to get about 60% in.
我赢的原因 是因为我只尝试进60%的球
Huh? You thought you'd be okay if you missed four shots?
咦？你觉得你四颗没进也没关系？
Yeah. So when I missed the first two, I didn't panic.
是的 所以当前面两球没投进去时 我并不紧张
But not you.
但你不是
You got the first two in and started to feel like you might win.
你进了两球 开始觉得自己可能会赢
And then you missed the fifth.
然后第五个球没投进去
I know what you were thinking.
我知道你那时在想什么
"I can't miss another shot!"
“我不能再失分了！”
"I'll get them all in!"
“我会全投进去！”
Ah, at that point Seto was panicking.
原来 那时濑户已经很紧张了
If you get nervous, you'll never win.
如果紧张就永远赢不了
So if he built a strategy ahead of time like you,
如果他像老师一样提前制定策略
he wouldn't have been nervous?
他就不会紧张？
Yes. That's how you separate the winners and losers.
是的 这就是赢家和输家的差别
But before an important day,
但重要的那一天到来之前
everyone gets nervous.
大家都会紧张
Especially people who have made a lot of effort.
特别是努力准备 非常用功的人
But those nerves are what made Seto lose, aren't they?
但那种紧张 正是濑户输掉的原因 对吧？
What can we do?
我们能怎么做呢？
Control your nerves.
控制你的紧张感
People who're good under pressure
那些在压力下还能好好表现的人
are aware that they feel nervous.
能意识到自己的紧张感
They expect mistakes and emotionally prepare.
他们预料到会有失误 做好心理准备
Listen. Don't try to be perfect.
听好了 别试图做得完美
Make sure you stay calm during the test.
考试时一定要保持冷静
Alright you guys!
好 你们大家！
From now until exam day, imagine yourself passing!
现在到考试那一天 想象你考上的样子！
The strong can imagine their own success!
强者能想象自己的成果！
And believe in yourself!
相信你自己
Why am I panicking?
我在紧张什么？
A couple of mistakes are no big deal.
几个失误不是什么大事
I'm going to get into UTokyo.
我会考进东大的
I just need to calm down and keep it steady.
我只需要冷静下来 保持稳定的状态
Imagine myself passing! Believe in myself!
想象自己考上的样子 相信自己
Alright!
好！
DAY 2 OF THE COMMON TEST
（大学入学共通考试 第二天）
Just solve the questions you know.
总之先解会的题目
This is a basic question, so I have to get the points.
这是基础问题 所以我都能得分
A=3x²-xy
A等于3x²减去xy
-9xy+3y²
减9xy加3y²
To solve this,
解这一道题
I use cosine and sine.
我要用到cos和sin
Differentiate 9x²-2x+2.
微分后 9x²减2x加2
The slope of the tangential line when x equals 1…
要求的切线倾斜度为X等于1时
C is a gingkgoaceae, so it's a gymnosperm.
C是银杏科 所以是裸子植物
Only angiosperms do double fertilization.
只有被子植物能双重受精
So it's B. Number two is the right answer!
所以答案是B 正确的答案是第二！
Ah, no, no, no, I'm running out of time.
糟糕！我没时间了
I'll do chemistry first.
我先做化学吧
Pencils down.
停笔
THE NEXT DAY
（隔天）
DAYS UNTIL THE UTOKYO SECONDARY EXAM
（东大二试 39天前）
Hand in your question sheets.
你们把试卷交上来吧
We'll check the answers.
我们会检查你们的答案
Wow, I'm so nervous.
哇 我好紧张
Okay, now study for the secondary exam.
好 现在为东大二试复习吧
Yes, sir.
是
Okay, here are the results.
成绩出来了
Hayase.
早濑
738 points.
738分
Huh? No way. Really?!
咦？不是吧 真的吗？
Iwasaki.
岩崎
752 points.
752分
Yay! It's higher than my goal!
太好了 这比我的目标还要高！
Kosugi.
小杉
810 points.
810分
It's lower than I thought…
比我预料的低…
Kenta.
健太
803 points.
803分
Yeah. Okay.
嗯 没问题
Amano.
天野
801 points.
801分
Huh?
什么？
801 points?!
801分？
Amano, that's amazing!
天野 太厉害了！
-Yeah! -Very well done.
-嗯！ -做得很好
You worked hard.
你真的很努力
Iwai. 484 points.
岩井 484分
Kohashi. 492 points.
小桥 492分
Too bad. You didn't get enough to pass.
很可惜 你们没有考到及格分
It wasn't enough for us.
我们果然还是不行
I hoped we could get it in one shot.
我还希望我们能够一举成功呢
But before, you couldn't have even gotten 300.
但在这之前 你们连300分都考不到
The results from your studies are showing. You did well.
你们的学习成果已经显现出来了 你们做得很好
We'll take it again next year!
我们明年再来考！
You all gotta get into UTokyo for our sake!
你们要连我们的份一起考上东大喔！
-Okay. -Yeah.
-好 -嗯
And Fujii.
还有藤井
719 points.
719分
-And lastly Seto. -Yeah.
-最后是濑户 -嗯
620 points.
620分
Huh?
什么？
620 points? What does that mean?
老师 620分有机会吗？
Honestly, it's going to be tight.
老实说 会有点难
With this score,
以这个分数
it's impossible without a miracle.
没有奇迹是不可能的
Hey Seto, where are you going?
喂 濑户 你去哪？
It's impossible, right?
反正不可能 对吧？
I have no chance of passing. There's no point.
我不可能会考上 这就没有意义了
I'll take it next year with the guys.
我明年再和他们一起考
Seto.
濑户
Seto might not make it…
濑户应该做不到了…
Fujii's score was lower than expected.
藤井的分数比预料中低
That kid really does crumble under pressure.
他真的很不擅长面对正式考试
Anyhow, we'll have the results in a month.
无论如何 我们一个月后就会拿到成绩
I trust you adjusted your attitude.
我相信你已经调整了心态
O-Of course.
当…当然了
Are you crying?
你在哭吗？
I'm not crying.
我没哭
You're fine.
你没事的
With that score, you'll make the cutoff.
那个分数够你通过门槛了
Are you scared of failing?
你怕落榜吗？
I'm scared.
我怕啊
Always.
一直都怕
Fujii.
藤井
Why do you want to go to UTokyo?
你为什么想上东大？
Because it's the top university in Japan, right?
因为它是日本最顶尖的大学 对吧？
That's right.
是的
It has to be the number one or it doesn't matter.
它不是日本第一就没意义了
Nobody will take me seriously!
没人会把我当回事！
Well then, Fujii.
这样的话 藤井
You should change to Humanities.
你转去文科吧
There's still time before you submit your application.
距离提交二试申请还有时间
Change to Humanities 3.
转到文科三类
Change from science to the arts?
从理科转到文科？
You know it yourself.
你自己也很清楚
If you go ahead with Sciences 2,
要是你继续考理科二类
your math and science scores are too low.
你数学和理科分数太低了
I bet you tripped up on Math 2 and Math B
想必是在 考数学二和数学B时遇到难关
and messed up your priorities with physics and chemistry.
扰乱了你物理和化学的作答优先顺序
I can't switch to Humanities this late!
现在哪来的及转组！
You can. You'd be surprised how many students switch and get in.
可以 要是你知道有多少考生 转组还考上了 你会很惊讶的
Most Humanities students aren't great at math.
文科的大多数考生数学都不太强
That's how you get ahead.
这就是你的优势
That's bullshit! I've spent three years working towards a science major, studying.
别开玩笑了！ 我这三年一直是以理科为目标
I have! Me!
我…
Not willing to switch to get in?
不愿为了进东大而转组？
-Your pride won't allow it? -You know it!
-你的自尊心不允许？ -你明明知道的！
Because you won't beat your brothers?
因为你没法胜过你的哥哥们？
Fail to get into UTokyo because of stubborn pride
因为这固执的自尊心而上不了东大
or get in, and stand at the starting line that is UTokyo.
或是考进去 站在东大的起跑线上
Which do you choose?
你会选择哪个？
Fujii.
藤井
Stop living life based on what others think.
别再按照其他人的想法过生活了
No matter what your parents or brothers say,
无论你父母和哥哥们怎么说
switching to Humanities is not shameful.
转到文科不是令人羞耻的事
If someone laughs at you, bring them to see me.
要是谁笑你 带他来见我
Okay?
好吗？
UTokyo is just the start.
东大只是一个开始
It's not for someone else or for acceptance.
不是为了别人 也不是为了被接受
Go to UTokyo for yourself!
为了自己上东大吧！
It doesn't matter if it's the arts or science. UTokyo is UTokyo!
文科也好理科也好 东大就是东大！
Shed your shame and reputation.
丢掉你的羞耻和名誉
Choose success. Stop at nothing.
选择那条成功的路 勇往直前
I know you can do it.
我知道你做得到的
Be confident.
自信点
Fujii.
藤井
I…
我…
I'll quit Sciences 2,
我会弃考理科二类
and test for Humanities 3.
转向文科三类
-Huh? -Is that even possible?
-什么？ -这可能吗？
English 80, math 60.
英语80分 数学60分
Fujii can get enough points with English and math.
藤井的英语和数学 就能凑到足够的分数
Literature 70, geography and history 50.
语文70分 地理和历史50分
With that, he'll have a passing score of 260.
这样的话 他就会以260分通过
But, studying for arts now?
不过 现在才开始学文科？
Everyone, please.
大家 拜托了
Huh? Fujii, what's going on?
咦？等等 藤井 你怎么了？
Teach me literature and history.
请教我语文和历史
If you'll have me,
如果你愿意
ask anytime.
可以随时问我
You can borrow my history notes.
我可以借你我的历史笔记
I can help with literature.
我可以帮助语文的部分
Fujii.
藤井
Well said.
做得好
Get what help you can.
尽可能去寻求帮助吧
Yes, sir.
是
Alright everyone, help him out.
好了大家 来帮帮他吧
NAO HAYASE
（早濑菜绪）
GET INTO UTOKYO!!
（目标考进东大！）
HUMANITIES 3
（文科三类）
I understand.
我明白了
Alright, tomorrow it is.
之后再告知你们时间
That was the former chairman.
是前任理事长
He's holding an emergency board meeting tomorrow about selling the school.
他明天会召开紧急理事会议 讨论出售学校的事
We've got to fight to protect this school.
我们得为保住这间学校而战斗
I'm ready. Are you, Mizuno?
我准备好了 水野可以吧？
Yes, Mr. Takahara.
是 高原老师
Let's see what they've got first.
先看看他们手上有什么吧
Mr. Sakuragi, Ms. Mizuno. As the school's consulting lawyers,
樱木老师 水野老师 作为学校的顾问律师
could you come to the meeting?
你们能出席明天的会议吗？
Of course. Right, sir?
当然了 对吧老师？
Whatever you say.
悉听尊便
Everyone, for the students of Tatsumi Gakuen,
那么大家 为了龙海学园的学生
let's do all we can.
尽我们的全力吧
Yes, ma'am.
是
You're home.
你回来了
Hey.
嗯
I bet you're hungry.
你一定饿了吧
Is ramen okay? With extra pork.
拉面怎么样？加叉烧
Sure.
好啊
Okay.
嗯
Is Seto okay?
濑户没事吧？
Who knows.
谁知道呢？
-Sir! -More importantly, you're ready?
-老师！ -更重要的是 你准备好了吗？
No matter who comes, I'll give them a smack-down.
无论来的是谁 我都会把他们打败
I get to pull out all the stops!
很久没干那么大件事了！
I wonder what sort of dirty lawyer they've got working for them?
不知道对方请了多么下流的律师
It's starting soon. Sit down.
快开始了 坐吧
Yes, ma'am.
是
They've arrived.
他们到了
Sakuragi.
樱木
Do you think you can get five kids into UTokyo?
你认为自己能将 五位学生送进东大吗？
Everyone's here.
大家都到了
Who is this?
这是谁？
They're leading the project.
他们会主导这项目
From Jager Corporation, Mr. Matsubara and Mr. Kajitani.
来自耶格尔企业的 松原先生和梶谷先生
Good to meet you. I'm the project leader, Matsubara.
初次见面 我是这项目的负责人松原
I'm Kajitani. Nice to meet you.
我是梶谷 请多多指教
Please, have a seat.
请坐
Is this everyone?
全员到齐了吗？
No, I invited my consultant lawyer to come.
不 我还请来了我的顾问律师
Come in.
进来吧
Pardon me.
不好意思
Ms. Kishimoto!
岸本律师！
Ms. Mizuno. What's wrong?
水野律师 怎么了吗？
Cat got your tongue?
舌头被猫叼走了？
What is going on?
这是怎么回事？
Please, don't act so surprised.
请不要表现得那么惊讶
The lawyer helping with the purchase is you?
那个协助出售的律师是你？
On that day…
该不会那天…
This is a nice place.
这是个好地方
Cape Taibusa is wonderful.
大房岬真的很棒
You said you came here for work,
你当时说你来这里工作
but it wasn't a coincidence.
但那不是巧合吧
Yes. I began coming here regularly long before you did.
是的 在你来之前 我就经常过来这里了
On business.
来出差
Ah, yes, let me introduce my two excellent assistants.
对了 我来介绍我两位出色的助手
Come in.
进来吧
Huh?!
什么？
Long time no see, senpai.
好久不见 前辈
Sakamoto… why?
坂本…为什么？
It's "President Sakamoto." I've helped you out a lot.
是“坂本社长”哦 我帮了你不少忙
Right, sempai?
对吧 前辈？
You were one year apart at Ryuzan, weren't you?
你们在龙山时只差一个年级 对吧？
We were UTokyo classmates.
我们在东大是同学
Long time no see. Mr. Sakuragi. Ms. Mizuno.
好久不见 樱木老师 水野老师
Yoneyama too. Why are you here?
还有米山 你为什么在这？
Oh, didn't I tell you?
我没告诉你吗？
We've teamed up with Ms. Kishimoto.
我们和岸本律师合作
We're working on the IT for this project.
在这个项目负责信息技术的部分
Yoneyama is helping me.
米山在协助我
-He's really brilliant. -You didn't tell me!
-他真的很优秀 -你没跟我说过！
-Sorry about that. -Since when?
-不好意思 -什么时候开始的？
Since before you two came.
你们俩来这里之前
So you knew all about the sale from the beginning?
所以你从一开始就知道出售的事？
Mr. Sakuragi and I joined this school
樱木老师和我加入了学校
and began helping with the rebuild.
开始帮忙重建的时候
You lied about supporting us?
你说支持我们 都是骗人的？
I was just as surprised as you!
我也和你一样惊讶！
You asked for help finding Mr. Sakuragi.
你请我帮忙找樱木老师
I never guessed the school you two were helping
我没想到你们俩帮助的学校
was this one!
就是这一间！
What a coincidence!
真是个巧合啊
You've been laughing at us this whole time.
这段时间 你一直都在嘲笑我们吧
You even involved Yoneyama.
你甚至把米山牵涉进来
You misunderstand, Ms. Mizuno.
你误会了 水野老师
After the accident,
那起事件后
Mr. Sakamoto has helped me a lot.
坂本先生帮助了我很多
I finally got into UTokyo after two years thanks to Mr. Sakamoto.
我两年后终于进入了东大 多亏坂本先生
Unlike someone else I could mention.
和其他某人不同
I'm healthy and doing well now
我很健康 也过的很好
thanks to Mr. Sakamoto and Ms. Kishimoto.
全都要感谢坂本先生和岸本律师
This is good real-world experience for me.
这对我来说是个很好的社会经验
What is this?
这都是什么啊？
These past two years, do you know how hard…
过去两年 你能想象我到底有多难…
Can we begin?
我们可以开始了吗？
Chairman, can we get down to business?
理事长 我们可以谈公事了吗？
Yes.
是
Mr. Matsubara, go ahead.
松原先生 请开始
Yes. I'm sure you already know.
是 我想你们已经知道了
We aim to start construction in 2022.
我们计划在2022年开始动工
See here.
请看这里
The red sections are areas we've already acquired.
红色的部分是我们已经购得的地区
Ours is the only piece left.
只剩我们这一块了
I won't sell this school.
我不会卖掉这间学校
It's the last bastion for the community.
这是这社区最后的堡垒
For the sake of the students, we can't close the school.
为了学生 我们不能关闭学校
Sorry.
真是抱歉
But if Mr. Sakuragi gets five students into UTokyo,
不过 如果樱木老师 将五位学生送进东大
I've heard you'll have to leave this school.
我听说你就得离开这间学校
-Right? Mr. Tatsuno. -Yes.
-对吧 龙野先生？ -是
I'll make sure you keep your promise, Kumiko.
你得信守约定 久美子
I will keep my promise.
我会遵守那个约定
Of course you will get five students in, won't you?
你当然能把五位学生 送进东大 对吧？
-Mr. Sakuragi. -No.
-樱木老师 -不
It's seven.
是七位
All seven will get into UTokyo.
他们七位都会考上东大
Did you hear that, Chairman?
你听见了吗 理事长？
Time to stop acting foolish.
是时候停止你无谓的行为了
Why don't you admit defeat
或许你可以认输
and start getting ready to leave?
准备离开了？
It's you who should admit defeat and leave.
你才是那个得认输离开的人
Ms. Kishimoto, I'm sure you're familiar with the school's articles of endowment?
岸本律师 我想你很熟悉 这间学校的捐赠条款吧？
Yes, of course.
是 当然了
The Tatsumi Gakuen articles of endowment.
龙海学园的捐赠条款
In other words, the basis for operating this school.
也就是说 这间学校的运行基础
What are you saying?
你在说什么？
To think that this clause had been added.
这条款会被加进去
I had no idea.
我真是完全没头绪
June 3, 2019.
2019年6月3日
Submitted to MEXT. Additional clause article 6, paragraph 9.
提交到文部科学省的 增加条款第六条第九款
It says this.
是这么写的
"Even if the chairman is elected by a majority of the board of directors,
“即使理事长是由 大多数理事选举而来…
if three-quarters of the teaching staff file an objection,
如果有四分之三的教职员反对
it will be rejected."
这就会被否决”
If we… no.
举例来说…不
When we get five or more students into UTokyo,
当我们把五位或以上的学生送进东大
according to the contract, Chairman Kumiko must quit.
根据合同 久美子理事长必须退出
Even if the previous chairman is selected to be chairman,
即便前任理事长被选为理事长
according to this amendment, if over three-quarters of staff say no,
根据这项增加条款 如果有四分之三的教职员反对
it's a no-confidence vote.
这就是一场不信任投票
All of the teachers here are against the sale.
这里的所有教师都反对出售
A chairman who wants to sell
一个要出售学校的理事长
will never be able to be chairman.
是永远不会当上理事长的
In other words, this school
也就是说 这间学校
will not be handed over to you.
不会被交到你手上
When I was on business overseas,
当我在海外出差时
you went to all the trouble to sneak the amendment in.
你费了那么大功夫 偷偷加了这增加条款
I guess you intended to use it to unseat me as chairman
我想你当时是打算用它 来把我从理事长的位置拉下去吧
and quietly submitted the application.
还悄悄提交了申请
And now I'm using it to have your neck.
现在 我正是利用它来对付你
You never thought of that?
你没想过还可以这样吧？
Kumiko…
久美子…
Even if I am unseated as chairman,
即使把我从理事长的位置拉下来
if over three-quarters of teaching staff are opposed,
要是有四分之三的教职员反对
you will never become chairman.
你也是不可能当上理事长的
We will get seven students into UTokyo.
我们会把七位学生送进东大
And we won't give up this school.
我们不会放弃这间学校的
Mr. Sakamoto. No…
坂本先生 不…
Sakamoto.
坂本
You betrayed us and that's serious.
你背叛了我们 这是件严重的事
Yoneyama, you should distance yourself from this case.
米山 你应该和这案子保持距离
If you want to stay clean.
如果你想保持清白的话
But I wonder.
但我在想
Would over three-quarters of staff
四分之三的教职员
choose your side?
真的会站在你那边吗？
Huh? Don't be ridiculous.
什么？你在说什么？
Right, Mr. Takahara?
对吧 高原老师？
Leave it to me.
交给我
Come in!
请进
If you're in favor of selling the school, go to the former chairman.
要是同意出售学校 请往前任理事长那边走去
If you're opposed, stand with the current chairman.
要是反对 就站在现任理事长这边
Go ahead.
请
Mr. Takahara, didn't you get approval?
高原老师 你不是获得同意了吗？
Oh, I did.
对啊
All of them approved my proposal.
他们都同意了我的提案
Yes, yes.
是的…
That means…
这意思就是…
Yes, just like me,
也就是说 和我一样
they approve the sale of the school.
他们都同意出售学校
-Huh? -Vice Principal, what is this?
-什么？ -教导主任 这是怎么回事？
Oh, shut it.
少来了
I have always
我一直都
hated you.
很讨厌你
The thought of not seeing your face
想到再也不用看到你的脸
gives me a thrill.
我就很爽快
Thanks, Mizuno.
水野 谢谢你
I didn't know about that article.
我不知道有那条款
The plan was almost spoiled.
计划几乎要泡汤了
I'm lucky to have such a smart former student.
我有那么优秀的学生 真是幸运
Thanks.
谢谢
I found the clue to preventing the sale of the school!
我找到了阻止学校出售的线索！
We can use this, Mizuno!
我们能用上这个 水野！
You were a traitor all along?
你从一开始都是叛徒？
Yes.
是
This is bullshit!
少来了！
-Oh! -You always told everyone to work hard.
-哦！ -你一直叫大家加油
You pretended to support us. That's a low blow.
你假装支持我们 真是卑劣
Sakamoto. Yoneyama.
坂本 米山
Did you forget everything Mr. Sakuragi taught you?
樱木老师教过的你们都忘了吗？
Now, now. Don't get upset, Mizuno.
那个嘛 别沮丧嘛 水野
You got duped.
你中计了
Anyway, I can't wait!
总之 我等不及了
This is going to become a resort complex!
这里将成为一个度假村
Schools don't make money anyway.
学校也赚不了钱嘛
And we weren't even at capacity.
反正也招不到足够的学生
The world is money, money, money.
这世界就是钱…
Listen, Mizuno. Remember this.
听着 水野 记住了
Those closest to you are the most dangerous.
最亲近的人是最危险的
Didn't they teach you that at UTokyo?
东大没教过你这点吗？
You invited us to this school…
你邀请我们到这间学校时…
Yes. It was part of the plan all along.
没错 这最初就是计划的一部分
I thought Mr. Sakuragi was a sure thing.
我以为樱木老师一定会过来
And then you came!
但你来了！
That wasn't part of the plan.
那不在计划之中
After all, you're clearly out of your depth.
毕竟 你真是不太在行
I was so worried.
我当时好担心
But then Mr. Sakuragi came.
但樱木老师来了
The students are well on their way.
学生们都学得很顺利
Yes, yes, I'm so smart.
嗯 我太聪明了
And that's that, Ms. Mizuno.
就是这样 水野老师
You are relieved from your post. Dismissed.
你已经没用了 没用了
Good night.
晚安
Alright, please continue, Ms. Kishimoto.
那么 请继续 岸本律师
Thank you for your continued support, Vice Principal Takahara.
以后请你继续关照了 高原主任
Do your job properly to the end.
你要尽责做到最后一刻喔
Mr. Sakuragi.
樱木老师
It's not over.
还没结束
There's still one more.
还有一个人
It has to be a complete victory.
非得是压倒性胜利不可
I want to destroy them completely.
我绝对要彻底击垮他
I've invited a trusty guest.
我召集了可靠的帮手
Long time no see.
好久不见了
Huh?
什么？
Aren't you embarrassed?
你不觉得丢脸吗？
I felt like I wasn't alone. Thanks.
让我觉得我并非孤身一人 谢谢
Alright, I'm off.
好 我出发了
Dear god, let everyone pass.
神啊 请让大家都考上吧
"Next year"?
你在想什么啊？
This moment will decide your future.
现在这个瞬间将会创造未来
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻译：赵慈宇